[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the 261st episode of the
Ask a Bijit Show. I hope everybody is
doing great and let us say see who all
is there on the live chat with us today.
I can see Shiva Sai Yashwan Sudair Adjut
Web of Dangra Sumitagarwal Priyanchi Sud
Jimmy Geopolitical Dubet from from Indor
I think web of Dangra is from Tokyo in
Japan Davik Shrian Gojo uh Vine Esman
Satish Kumar Sharma Truthful Penguin
Pratam Sharma Slayer Arnab Mahita
Busetti uh Shivastai Shri Ramachandra
Namaha Animesh Paul, Sumit Agarwal,
Vinman again, Gojo Shuba, Shou Agarwal,
Sam the gamer, Slayer again, Anurraha,
Vinyas, Gopagor again, Sarang, Ninali,
Sentin, SP, Satish Kumar, Sharma,
Ganapati, Ra, Raja, Akash Kumar,
Sumitagwal, Rohan, Sunja, Summit Garwal
again, Prrenet Paul from Kolkata,
Manisha, Kardo, uh, who else do we have?
Shubhanker, Kulkarni, Sopesh, Kawas,
Pritam, Jimmy, Mandar, Hadkar, Aayush
Singh, Ashish, Udash, Vinyas again,
Sumit, Agarwal, Ichino, Senpai, Suba,
Jit, Gosh, Adita, Jal, Sarang, Ninali,
Sudashan, Ragavan, Ankit, Mahapatras,
Caitanya, Rashmir from Rajasthan,
Bridesh, Sri Jandas, Pratam Sharma,
Sudendra, Desai, Abijit, Raal, Akila,
Narayan,
SKK Pritam Kumar Rout meet mystery
Ashish Pandel and many many other people
adai
SHX XR11 Arpan Sam the gamer Keshav
and so many other people random skull
again helloar
Kalborgi anonymous scientist is back
xenomorphosis mlevin is here Ankita is
hereund
and so many other people. So, thank you
so much for being here on the live chat
and let's take some questions. What
questions do we have today? Let's take
this one first. Sam the Gamer says, "Can
somebody Okay, here I am. I found it. I
saw it. So, I'll take it." Uh, the
Vakhan corridor of Afghanistan, how is
it important for India? What's the
Vakhan corridor? Why is it important?
How is it important? We'll have to go
and take a look at the map. I'll have to
crack out the map. It's not open yet.
Let me open it. Let me deploy it. Uh
let's deploy the map and take a look at
the Wakhan corridor. Now what is the
deal with the Wakan corridor? Okay,
where's the map? We start today's
session with the map.
So here is the geography of the
subcontinent and we are talking about
the Wakhan corridor which means that we
would go to northern India and beyond
the present day boundaries of northern
India.
So the Wakhan corridor is this strip of
land that belongs to Afghanistan which
is sandwiched between Pakistan occupied
Gilgit Baltasan Jammu and Kashmir and
Tajakistan and some part of it is also
connected to uh Shinjang Chinese
occupied Singinjang that is the Vakhan
corridor
now in the future when India uh regains
uh the territory that's currently
temporarily occupied by Pakistan which
is Gilgit Baltistan PJK PO Gilad
Baltistan etc. Then we will have this
connection with Afghanistan via the
Vakhan corridor the Vakhan National
Park. Now this is a very mountainous
region. If you look at the satellite
image, you can see it's all mountainous.
Mountains all over the place. It's fully
frozen as you can see, right? It's a
very mountainous region. It's very hard
to traverse.
And uh that's the deal. So the
importance of the Vakhan corridor is
that when we once again have our
connectivity with Afghanistan, this part
of Afghanistan will be our u essentially
our corridor or our gateway to Central
Asia. That is the importance of the
Wakhan corridor which is pretty evident
from uh the map. So that is your answer
sir. Now let's take some of the super
chats. I can see Shubhankar has a
question. I failed to understand why the
current regime in Iran has problems from
with Israel from the start. Their prime
enemy was always Saudi Arabia. Why pick
a fight with Israel? Iran fights with
while Saudi prospers. Well, I could give
you another 90-minute explanation or you
can just watch
you can just watch the episode that just
streamed live like 5 minutes ago, which
is geostrategy episode 7 in which I have
gone deep deep into these matters. I've
done a very deep dive into what is the
deal between Israel and Iran. They used
to have cooperation. They were allies of
of of sorts during the regime of the
Iranian dictator the the Sha Muhammad
Raza Palvi. Then there was the Iranian
revolution 1979 where they became
enemies and the Iranian regime saw
Israel as an illegitimate state and the
small shaitan the shaitan abuser was the
US and so on. Then there was the Iran
Iraq war 1980 to 1988 in which uh the
two nations Iran and and Israel were
officially enemies publicly enemies but
privately and secretly they were allies
and Israel was supporting arms and
ammunition to Iran to ensure that Iran
doesn't is not defeated by Saddam
Hussein's Iraq and then once the war was
over they again became full-scale
enemies and Iran started developing a
nuclear program and Israel sees that as
an exist existential threat. They say
that they should be the only nuclear
power in the region and Iran should not
have nuclear weapons and so on. So it's
a long story. If you want to get to the
bottom of that, please watch episode 7
of geostrategy that will be available on
the channel. Now
um Gapati, thank you very much sir.
Appreciate your contribution. Rohan Suna
says his majesty Karan Tapper says
operation cinder was a blunder. Well, I
don't take Mr. Karan Tapar seriously. So
let's there's no point discussing his
opinions.
Ananda Kishor says was Ambedkar on the
team Gandhi or team India. Look once
again let me reiterate I have not
studied the life and career of Mr. of
Dr. Ambedkar. So I don't know which team
he was on.
Dhiraj Khmed says I was born in Bahrain.
I have lived in Bahrain where my family
still lives. The US fifth fleet just
left Bahrain leaving them leaving
Bahrain vulnerable to Iran. What are
their reasons to worry, let's take a
look at the map. Okay, so that everybody
understands what we're talking about.
Where is Bahrain? Small small little
nation but important nation. Very small
nation but important nation. This here
is Bahin. See this little tiny little
nation here. Even smaller than Qatar.
Um
so the US fifth fleet apparently has
just left Bahrain. I'm not aware of that
but obviously since you are from there
you will know what is happening. Does it
mean that if the US fifth fleet leaves
Bahrain does it mean that Bahin is now
vulnerable to Iran? So we are assuming
here that Iran is is a crazy nation that
wants to destroy everybody and Iran is a
big threat to everybody in the region. I
don't think that's the case. Iran in my
opinion just wants to be left alone and
let us do what we their message to the
world is that allow us to do whatever we
want. We are a sovereign nation. You got
you don't get to tell us whether we can
have nukes or not or what kind of
military capabilities we can have. We
are a sovereign nation. We'll develop
whatever is best for for our interests.
And maybe it is possible like some claim
that Iran has ambitions imperialistic
ambitions of its own. Well, many nations
have that, right? But does it mean that
if the US fifth fleet leaves Bahrain
then Iran is now guaranteed to smash
Bahin to bits? I don't think so. Bahrain
is a very important nation and a very
important ally of the US. And if Iran
for no reason attacks Bahrain, well, it
will invite significant trouble on
itself.
So I would say that this event of the US
fifth fleet just leaving Bahrain for
whatever deployment it is not
necessarily a reason to worry. What
could be a reason to worry? A
significant further escalation in the
conflict. maybe more Israeli strikes on
Iran or maybe if the US gets involved in
the war and tries to decapitate do a
decap decapitation strike on Iran or if
it tries to destroy the the the um
Iranian nuclear facilities like Furo for
example if such things happen then there
could be a reason to worry all across
the West Asia region all across the G
Gulf region it would mean that Iran may
hit all
US military bases in the region and and
potentially US allied nations as well.
That would be a reason to worry. So, I
don't think Iran is going to do
something crazy unless something crazy
is done to it.
Okay. WRV 1313 says, "Why has Trump
changed his stance on Pakistan?" Well, I
would recommend that you watch my
episode 5 of Geost Strategy in which
I've give gone into exhaustive detail as
to what Trump's dealings with Pakistan
are. Uh where is that? Let me put that
on the screen. One second. Give me a
second.
Uh,
okay. It's it's Geost Strategy episode
5. Give me a second. I'll put that on
the screen. Watch that. You will know
exactly what the deal is. I have I've
gone into incredible detail in that.
Nobody else has does this analysis, has
done the analysis. It is this episode
here, Geost Strategy episode 5, in which
I've spoken about the Ahmedabad air
crash and also about the Trump Pakistan
connection. So if you want to understand
why Trump is suddenly in love with
Pakistan, well then please watch that
episode. I will not repeat all of that
over here again because it'll be
counterproductive. It'll be redundant.
Watch the episode. I have answered your
question in great detail in that
episode.
Tjis says, "Is Udu considered an
official Indian language? If yes, in
which state I see hatred towards Udu in
many parts of India. How should we
Indians look at Udu? Um I have no idea
if Udu is considered to be an official
Indian language. I've seen sign boards
in some parts of India in certain very
major cities. I've seen sign boards in
Udu which kind of indicates that it
seems to be regarded as a as a as one of
the official Indian languages. I am not
sure which state. Okay. And uh well
hatred towards Udu or whatever that's a
whole different story. Look, you have to
understand what udu is. Udu is a mongrel
language. It's it's an amalgamation of
multiple languages. And this language
udu, what is the meaning of this word
udu?
The word udu or udu means camp in the
Turk Chagatai language which is also a
word in the Mongolian language because
the Turk languages are connected are
related genetically to the Mongolian
languages.
So it means a military camp. So this
language udu it emerged it it it evolved
in Turk military camps in India.
These military camps were part of the uh
infrastructure of occupation of India.
And in these military camps you had
people of various language with various
languages who had to communicate to each
other with each other. So you would have
some Indian vasals who who would speak
various prait based upper branch
languages
which were derived from Sanskrit. Then
you would have tur speakers who would
speak Turk languages like Chagatai. Then
you would have Persian speakers who
would speak Persian and you would have
people who would speak Arabic. So all
these languages amalgamated and a new
hybrid Mongrel language evolved which
was based on Sanskrit grammar. a lot of
Sanskrit vocabulary but also lots of
loan words came in from the Turk
languages from the Persian language from
the Arabic language and that gave rise
to this language called Udu so it's a
it's an Indian language sure it evolved
in India but it has a lot of foreign
influence and foreign loan words and and
it's it's not what you would call a
purely Indian language
some some could argue that way right so
maybe that's the reason why some people
have a hatred towards it I personally
have no great love for Udu right I don't
have any hatred for Udu but I don't have
any great love for Udu and so on
okay uh book rev says namaste first of
all what roles are Russia and China
playing in the Iran Israel conflict how
might their involvement shift the
regional dynamic so I have gone into
that also this question in the episode 7
of geost strategy that just concluded
it's there on the channel you can look
into it but the deal is this look I'll
obviously answer your
So both nations are allies, you could
say official, unofficial, whatever, but
they're allies of Iran. What's the
relationship between Russia and Iran?
First of all, Iran is supplying um has
been supplying Russia with drones,
kabikhaza drones, shahed drones for use
in the uh Ukraine conflict. That's been
going on for at least 2, three years.
And u so that's a great help that Iran
is providing to Russia. Russia is also
providing various kinds of military and
other assistance to to Iran. It is
supposed to sell be in the process of
selling uh one of the variants of the
Sukoy fighter plane to to Iran. So that
is an ongoing situation. So uh there is
this close relationship that Russia has
with Iran.
And then there's China. So, China and
Iran have st have signed a few years ago
a strategic deal, a 25-y year strategic
agreement in which China will invest, I
don't know, maybe $500 billion or
something worth of of money into uh
Iranian infrastructure and industries
and Iran as part of the agreement will
give China will will sell to China
tremendous quantities of energy which is
fossil fuels mainly oil and gas mainly
oil at reasonably discounted rates. So,
Iran is very important for China a
significant amount of cheap energy.
China will get from Iran and if Iran
suddenly becomes US vasal then it'll be
a it will be a big setback not just for
Russia but also for China. So it is in
Russia's interest it is in China's
interest for the Iranian government to
continue to exist and for a regime
change to not happen in the so they will
play various kinds of roles in this
matter. they will Russia will probably
want to mediate between u the US and
Iran and and and reach some and ensure
that some kind of agreement is reached
between the two nations. Mr. Putin could
offer his good offices uh for the in
this regard to Mr. Trump and to the
Iranian leadership and um so from Mr.
Putin's perspective he would want some
kind of agreement to be done to be
signed some kind of deal to be signed
between Iran and the US which may kind
of cap Iran's ability to pursue its
nuclear program and so on but it it will
at least ensure that a regime change
doesn't happen. So both Russia and China
are deeply invested in Iran and they
both would be would not want a regime
change to happen or a destruction of the
Iranian military capabilities to happen.
Adwit says, "What impact did Ronald
Reagan have as president?" He was a very
he was one of the probably the last
great US president. Um he was obviously
a Republican, was a conservative and he
was a he probably was the guy who
presided over the slow disintegration
of the USSR
and his economic policies were good. He
launched a war on on drugs in in in
Central and South America, Operation
Condor. I don't think anybody remembers
that today. So, he had a pretty big
impact as a US president. He was
president for two terms and in my
opinion, he's the last great US
president. After that, you we've not had
a great US president. Now, Chiket says,
"Won't Israel have a major fuel deficit
if war breaks out?" No, they won't. They
have a good understanding with various
Arab nations.
The Arab nations also see Israel as a
threat or see Iran as a threat.
So, Israel has a good understanding with
various Arab nations like Saudi Arabia,
like uh the UAE, like Qatar etc. And
they will get fuel from these nations.
Of course, if a war breaks out, if
there's a closure of the state of
hormones, if there's instability, then
there's going to be a fuel crisis
globally, not just for Israel, but
Israel is in the region. So, it'll be
actually easier for for Israel to get
fuel. It'll be more difficult for the
rest of the world to get um continuing
supplies of of u of fossil fuels, mainly
oil, from the Gulf region.
Um,
your average tech enthusiast says, "If
the US had stayed in the JCPOA, would
Iran have delayed its nuclear program?"
Well, according to the terms and
conditions of the JCPOA, the joint
comprehensive plan of action, Iran was
supposed to cap its nuclear program and
the the details you can you can look up.
But yes, if if uh the US had stayed, if
the US had not walked out of the JCPOA,
then what would have happened is that
there would have been sanctions relief
for Iran. So some of the sanctions would
have been undone and in exchange for
that, Iran would have capped its nuclear
program. It would not have it would have
allowed IAEA inspectors to oversee its
nuclear activities its nuclear program
and they would have agreed to not cap to
not uh enrich uranium beyond a certain
limit. Maybe it's 60% maybe it's some
other I don't remember what it was but
there was a cap. So then Iran would have
delayed its nuclear program for sure
100% if the US had stayed in the JCPOA
but the US said that we have received
intelligence that the Iran is going
ahead with something or the other and
that's why this deal is no longer valid
and Mr. Trump walked out unilaterally of
the JCPOA which then has given Iran the
excuse or the go-ahad the green signal
that if the guy I signed the deal with
has walked out then I can do whatever I
want. So that's how it works.
Uh VS says, "What's the most authentic
or accurate book on the JFK
assassination?" I have not read any
books on the JFK assassination. I would
imagine if you want to know more about
it, you would want to read uh
um Oliver Stone has written a book about
this. He's a filmmaker of course is also
made two movies about this. One is a is
a movie that stars Kevin Cosner.
It's called JFK. And then more recently
he has come up with a with a you know an
updated documentary about the JFK
assassination and uh and I'm sure I
believe Oliver Stone has also written a
book as an uh to accompany the
documentary. So maybe that is a good
place to look into. I personally have
not read any full any entire book on the
on the matter. So I can't can't recall
properly but I would say look into the
documentary by J by by Oliver Stone. You
can watch the movie also and there's a
book that accompanies the second more
recent documentary. So maybe that will
be a good good place to uh get authentic
and accurate information. Of course
there are lots of people who will say
that it's it's conspiracy theories.
There are lots of people who will say
that what the Warren Commission says is
the right thing. But clearly the Warren
Commission is wrong. The Warren
Commission said that there was a single
shooter who shot the president from the
back from behind. If you watch the
Zapora film, you can see it's clearly
somebody from the front front who has
shot JFK. You can see his head recoil
backwards while his head explodes. So,
come on.
Okay.
He's Manticor says, "What could dark
matter be useful or for if found out? We
have no idea."
uh see dark matter right now it's a
complete mystery. It is clearly some
kind of particle or family of particles
or something that um interacts only
gravitationally most likely cold dark
matter and if it interacts only
gravitationally if it's so small that
there's nothing we can do about it to
use it with the current state of our
technology. We are an electromagnetic
species. The world we live in is an
electromagnetic world. without
electromagnet without electromagnetism
we see nothing we sense nothing and
gravity is something we perceive only
very weakly so even if we discover what
dark matter actually is I don't think
we'll be able to utilize it in any way
whatsoever scientifically industrially
commercially or whatever for a few
centuries
in the long run I I don't know maybe if
dark matter can is a is is something
that can be annihilated to produce
energy maybe that could be a fuel source
long down the road. So maybe the dark
matter could annihilate. For example, if
dark matter is made up of primordial
black holes, quantum bound states of
primordial black holes, then maybe you
could somehow induce it to annihilate,
which would give you Hawking radiation,
which is a tremendous source of energy
potentially. So maybe down the line, a
few centuries down the line, we could
potentially use it if that turns out to
be the case.
Um, feminist slayer, etc.
says, "Why didn't Russia colonize
Americas like the European powers?"
Well, Russia, if you look at its
geographical location, it's a Eurasian
power. Um, now let's go to the map. The
map will tell us, will give us the
answer. See, if you look at the map,
yes, we can see, see, today Russia is
just gigantic nation. But historically,
Russia has been this region around
Moscow and Kiev. the Kiev region. Kiev
was the original capital of the RS
people, the Kiev and Rus. And then later
after the Mongolian yoke was thrown off.
Moscow became a big deal and Moscow
became the capital. So this region was
essentially the the homeland of the
Slavic the Roose people. Okraina was the
borderlands and Moscow and its
principalities surrounding
principalities St. Petersburg etc. Sank
Petersburg etc were the major cities and
that's what where Russia was. So it was
a um an a Eurasian landbased power. It
had access to the oceans but to the sea
but all frozen the north the north sea
the baron sea uh and so on. Then later
Russia expanded eastwards eastward
eastwards it was able to go all the way
to the far east and it eventually took
possession of Alaska which it eventually
later sold to the US. So because Russia
had so much territory that it had
conquered and expanded into uh and
because it was not a seafaring power, it
was just a land-based power. That's why
it did not colonize the Americas like
the other European powers which are all
maritime powers like the UK which is an
island, like Spain which is a peninsula
that is out there in the Atlantic Ocean
essentially and the Mediterranean and
the Portuguese once again a maritime
nation and of course the the the Danes
etc. they also historically were a
maritime power. Belgium later became a
deal but in Africa and so on. So because
Russia's because of Russia's
geographical position location that's
why because of that geography is is of
course one of the decisive factors in
geopolitics and and and in history and
that's why Russia did not uh proceed to
colonize the Americas the way the
European other European maritime powers
did.
Uh Amisha Mishra says what prize did Mr.
Munir Aim Munir of of Pakistan pay for
his free lunch with Trump. It was not a
free lunch. I assure you and that's why
you asking me about the price. Well,
once again I would say if you want the
answer to your question, a detailed
answer to your question, I would highly
recommend you watch episode 5 of
geostrategy in which I have gone into
the Trump Pakistan connection.
Okay. So Trump is
Trump is is hoping to grab a piece of
the Pakistan pie. He's his family his
business empire is invested is is
investing in Pakistan's cryptocurrencies
uh scene the stable coin scene etc. They
are going to make investments in
Pakistan's oil and gas se sector. They
want to tap into Pakistan's rare earth
sectors and all that and all of that is
going to that access is going to be
given exclusively essentially it looks
like to the Trump empire business
empire. So that's the price Mr. Munir
has paid and the military is very much
involved in this the Pakistani military.
That's why there is this great love that
Trump has developed for Pakistan because
the total value of all of this is in is
is around I would say 65 is it billions
or is it trillion? It's about 65
trillion overall the assets. How much
can be extracted remains to be seen but
that's the deal. So that's the price you
pay for a lunch with Trump if you are
the Pakistani dictator. The price is you
sell your country. You sell your
country's resources. Please Indians, my
dear Indian viewers, see it this way.
Pakistan is our ancestral territory that
is currently temporarily occupied by
terrorists. It's our ancestral lands.
Pakistan
it's for thousands of years it's been
part of our ancestral heritage right our
lands and those resources are our
resources that are temporarily occupied
by terrorists and who is now going to
plunder them the Trump empire
that's the price Mun has paid sold of
his country to get a lunch with Trump
MK says is India trying to have its own
ASML like China well eventually
Look, ASML is not a Chinese entity. ASML
is Dutch.
ASML. Let's let's Google ASML, shall we?
Quickly, let us go to our friend Google.
These days, I think people do chat GPD,
right? I I I still do Google. I'm I'm
oldfashioned. What is ASML?
So, ASML is a Dutch multinational
company that designs, develops,
manufactures, etc. Semiconductor
equipment. Okay. So, so ASML is Dutch
and the the major thing they make is
those photo lithography machines that
make that that etch do the etchings and
and create the architecture on silicon
that is the basis of the chips the
microp processors the chips the GPUs and
so on. So without those photo
lithography machines you will not have
those incredibly complicated and
powerful
chips GPUs etc. Right? So it's a very
important technology to have and this
technology has been developed over
decades and decades by this company and
I think it's it has a more than 90%
global share if I'm not mistaken I don't
remember the exact numbers right now but
very significant global share u ASML has
so for India to become a major
semiconductor player a major
semiconductor manufacturer exporter etc
and to be completely self-sufficient in
semiconductor connectors we will have to
develop our own technology similar to
what ASML has and that is obviously the
the great goal. Now, how long it takes
remains to be seen. We want to become a
major player by the 2030s. By 2030,
essentially the next 5 10 years maximum.
So, we'll have to do a lot of
um a lot of growing up essentially.
We'll have to develop very very uh
difficult technologies in this time
period. But yes, we would like to do
that and we that that is the the mission
we have given ourselves. That's the
mission that the government has given to
India and to itself.
Okay, Suranjun Kumar Biswar says, "What
are your thoughts on Pakistan's Molana
Tariq Jum claiming he's a descendant of
Pritar Johan through his son Ramdev
Johan?" Look, I'm not aware of of of
this claim by whatever Molana whatever.
It's possible that this molana may have
Chawan ancestry. There are lots of
Pakistanis who have Rajput ancestry.
But the moment you change your religion
and you start hating your ancestral land
and culture, I would say you are no
longer Rajput.
The what what is the prime
characteristic of of a Rajput? You love
your dharma and you love your culture,
civilization and you love your
motherland and you fight and die for it
if required. These these Pakistanis who
claim to be Rajputs, they want to
destroy India. They hate India. They
hate their own ancestral culture. How
can they then claim we are descendants
of Pira Johan? Even if they are, who
cares? You have betrayed your ancestor,
your great ancestor by by by
being who you are today. So I don't
know. I don't care about the veracity or
not of this claim. It is just uh
maybe it's it's uh something this
gentleman this individual is doing to to
to
uh position himself highly and and to
create some kind of a buzz for himself
and some kind of name for himself to
claim ancestry from a great man that
sort of thing. I don't even know if
Pritur Johan had a son called Ramdev
Johan. So maybe this is all fabricated.
Even if it's true, I don't care because
once you once you
convert to a foreign religion, it's fine
if you want to. But once you do that,
you're no longer a Rajbut. Once you hate
your own ancestral culture, once you
hate your own ancestors, you hate your
own motherland, you are no longer a
Rajbut. Come on. So I don't care.
Har says, "Genealogologists confirmed
that prototuric people had mixed
and Caucasian ancestry.
Western Gauthur had nearly European 100%
europe European uralic ancestry even
before migrating to Anatolia
showing deep roots in Eurasian genetics.
Well, I'll tell you the actual
prototype. Okay, I'm sure this is done.
Okay, I've not looked it up, but uh I'm
sure you must have done your own due
diligence and you must have found this.
That's why you're telling me. So u noted
first of all noted what you're saying.
Secondly the real protokurks were the sh
new people. Let's Google it. Okay. Who
are the sh new people? It's a very
strange uh spelling that we have. Okay.
But let's go here.
The new people. These were a nomadic
confederation. The they were essentially
the cousins of the ancestors of today's
Mongols.
Okay. And if we look at the where these
people had an empire, they essentially
had an empire where the the Mongols
exist today. So the Sha and the and the
Mongols were essentially the same
people. If you go back maybe 2 and a
half thousand years or so. So if we go
back to Indian history, how did things
work? You had first of all uh Indogreek
kingdoms in the northwest in the in the
Gandhar region right Indogreek kingdoms
you had great dharmic kings like Milinda
etc manander and so on and eventually
the indoor Greeks just assimilated into
the Indian population then what happened
after the Indo Greeks is that the
skitans invaded the shakas invaded India
north northern India started from
Gandhar and then eventually they settled
down in western and conquered and
settled in western northern India and so
on so forth the great bahhatrapas The
Skians were the same people as us
genetically.
But why did the skithians invade?
Because they were being pressurized by
the Kushans. So why were the Kushans
pressurizing the the Skithians in their
territory? Because the Kushans were
being pressurized by the Huns, the Shu,
the people who originated in present day
Mongolia. So those are the actual protot
Mongol Caucasian ancestry. That's about
2 and a half thousand years before
today. If you go back to the so-called
prototypes from 18800 years ago, they
may have mixed mixed kaucan industry. If
you look at the prototypes from 1500
years ago, they may have definitely
Caucasian ancestry mixed with
ancestry. But the original shu from 2
and a half thousand years ago, they were
purely Mongolic Turk. No Caucasoid
ancestry that I can think of. And the
the Kushans of course had what today
they would call Caucasoid ancestry. If
you look at the Tarin basin river
mummies, you will see that many of them
have red hair or blonde hair and they
seem to have light skin. But if you look
at the gods they worship and the
language they spoke. There's nothing
cockazard or European about that. It's
very drabic and so on. So history is
super complicated. Super complicated.
But interesting fact that you brought
out over here. So thank you for that.
Hershey says what's a honey trap and
when was it started how does it work in
other different countries was it used in
ancient India honey trap is vishkanyas
you know chanaka wishtuk chanaka had
this practice you want to trap officials
from from uh enemy nations or enemy
enemy territories you honey trap them
using wish kanyas wish kanyas would
sometimes poison the guy or sometimes
ent trap the guy in in a love affair and
that's how by entrapping the guy and
fascinating the By seducing the guy, the
official, high-ranking official, you can
get all the state secrets. That's a
honey trap. As simple as that. What's a
honey trap? It's compromising a high
ranking or important person by having
them engage in a romantic or sexual
affair with one of your agents who is
pretending to be a normal person,
usually a female. That's a honey trap.
Okay, that's that's what that's the term
they use. It's it's I suppose it's
always been around. You read about read
read the Art Shastra you will find that
there right the Artastra was written two
and a half thousand years ago roughly
and I suppose every country has its way
of doing things the Chinese use this
technique against Americans
as of now and uh so on so yeah that's a
deal
um UC says can you tell us what the CIA
is the central investigative agency
gency. The CIA is one of the two
threeletter agencies that I know of that
I can think of off the top of my head.
The other is the FBI, the Federal Bureau
of Investigation. The FBI is the
domestic intelligence agency within the
US within the territorial boundaries of
the United States. And the CIA is the
foreign intelligence wing that does
spying activities, destabilizing
activities, regime change operations,
quasi terroristic activities, drug
operations, all the nastiest things you
can think of in the world, the CIA does
that. So as the US, the United States
has this foreign intelligence and and
destabilization wing, which is the CI,
the CIA,
and they have the CIA field manual. And
some of these things have been
declassified. If you read them, they're
pretty nasty stuff. But you know, if
you're a nasty person, you you'll learn
something from th those things. And they
are the ones who taught
the Afghan mahin how to use terrorism as
as strategy of course for liberating
Afghanistan from the Soviets. But then
that was then repurposed to the Kashmir
terrorism.
And they also had similar practices in
South America, Central America and so
on. I mean why why is why is there so
much drug cultivation in these regions?
Well, there has to be a reason for that.
The first question you ask yourself is
who is consuming all the drugs?
Okay. Aries Manticor says, "Is it
possible due to the green revolution
dals legumes were selectively grown to
contain more carbs instead of proteins?
Should we try to create superior GMO
variants to reduce carb and increase
proteins? I don't think the green
revolution had the uh objective of of
increasing the carb content of legumes,
dals, etc. The green revolution was the
objective was to create sufficient crops
for Indians by focusing on just a few
crops.
So India has always had this tremendous
biodiversity.
All kinds of different uh crops existed.
Crops that are almost unknown today.
Very few people eat them. Uh these days
it's again becoming slightly more
popular. You know crops like bajar,
jawar etc. various kinds of mazes we had
in India and so on so forth. Today it's
just two three kinds of rice and two
three kinds of wheat. In wheat also we
had so much diversity but only a few
strains of wheat are now prevalent in
India. So a lot of the bio biodiversity
was was wiped out because of the green
revolution. So it did solve the problem
that India had of being a tremendously
impoverished and uh undernourished
nation. It solved that problem but at
the cost of India's biodiversity. It
could have been done better for sure. No
question about it. But it did not have
the effect of selectively growing
legumes in such a way that there's more
carbs carb content and less protein
content. That's not the case. I don't I
don't think that's the case. Um should
we try and create superior GMO variance
to reduce carb and increase protein? I
think it's never a good idea to try and
fiddle with the genetic makeup of uh
organisms in an artificial way because
you may introduce certain issues that
will be apparent only 20 30 generations
down the line by and by that time
there's nothing much you can do about
it. Uh because see if you if you tweak
some genes it's going to have an effect
on the other genes in some way or the
other that we don't understand. There is
something called the dark matter of DNA.
So if you look at our genome, human
genome, pretty complicated gen genome,
right? We only understand 3 4% of it
about 95 96% of our genome, we don't
understand it at all. It seems to be
non-coding. It seems to be bits and
pieces of DNA code that are that don't
code for any proteins or anything. They
don't they don't seem to have any
purpose, but it's still there in our geo
genome and it's being passed on
generation after generation. So maybe it
has some use and if you mess with that
it may end up doing something terrible
to you down the line 20 30 generations
down the line potentially.
So the point is you know it is it is
very tempting to play god when you have
the tools but you have the tools and you
tweaking stuff but we don't understand
really what the long-term effects of
that are going to be. So I think it's
not a good idea in my opinion to try and
create superior GMO variance without
fully understanding the genome and what
it does.
Okay. Arun Arun says does Turkey still
deserve to be called the drone
superpower after the failure of Bikar in
the three-day war? Look all of this is
just uh much much of this is is is
propaganda and narratives. Okay. uh a
nation that produces lots of drones but
none of them have been tested in in
warfare. You can't call that nation a
drone superpower. And then when the
drones are actually tested in warfare,
we know what ended up happening in the
three-day war between Pakistan and
India. We destroyed all their drones.
The drones were completely ineffective.
I'm not sure what all drones were used.
Was the Kizilma used? Was the by by car
used? Were other drones used? But
whatever drones were used, many of them
were Turkish. Those were all wiped out
by India. So, I think that has caused a
significant dent to Turkeykey's
so-called reputation of being a drone
power. And I don't think Turkey really
deserves to be called a drone superpower
or whatever. Of course, they have
certain drones that seem to be very
high-end stealth with stealth
characteristics like the Kizilma drone,
the Red Apple and so on, but I'm not
sure if that has been battle proved
anywhere anywhere. So any system you can
tout it and and praise it to the high
heavens but the only real test is its it
its performance in battle. So that is
that still remains to be seen. So thus
far I would say Turkey doesn't deserve
that sort of title of being a drone
superpower.
Naman Singh says the history of the US
says that we can't rely on the US. We
are heavily dependent on the US. we
should make our own technological
ecosystem like our own messaging
application social media because the US
can choke us if they decide to do so by
banning. Well, I agree with you Naman
Singh, you are absolutely right. I
myself have been saying this for quite
some time. I have been uh uh doing these
shows for about 4 years now and I have
been saying this from the beginning that
we cannot uh have these dependencies
that could one day come to bite us in in
our backside, right? uh for example
India I think we we have a substantial
amount of the um I'm just giving a
different example here but we our
territory our land is is home to about
at least 10 to 20% of the world's rare
earth minerals but we don't have the
industry to extract them we don't know
how to extract them that's why we are
dependent on China and others and now
China has put export restrictions on
rare earth metals and rare earth magnets
and because of that we are in a
significant amount of crisis right now.
We have reserves only until the mid of
June. We have been forced to to stop
exporting rare earths to Japan even
though we have an agreement with Japan.
So when you have the when you have the
raw materials and resources but if you
don't develop them then you're going to
end up dependent on your enemies and to
develop the industries and the knowhow
and the capabilities and technologies to
to extract and process the raw raw earth
in India and in a usable way it's going
to take us a decade at least if we start
now a decade that's how stupid we have
been when it comes to other technologies
only when something bad happens that
that's that's when we wake
So once again when it comes to social
media if the if in the future the US
decides to cut off India from social
media then we will suddenly find
ourselves in position where we can't
communicate with each other as a nation
as a as a as a society. So you are right
we need to have our own technological
ecosystem. The Chinese have their own
complete stack. They don't need the US.
They have banned US apps. They've banned
US uh platforms from China. The Russians
have their own things. they have uh
Yandex is a search engine and they have
something else for social media and all.
So Russia and China have made sure that
they are not dependent on the US. We
have done no nothing of the sort which
is very short-sighted and very
disappointing. So I agree with you it
needs to be done.
Paris Viri says why is Iran so against
Israel?
Yeah. Well, look, long story. If you
want to understand properly, watch
episode 7 of geost strategy that
concluded 15 minutes ago. Concluded 45
minutes ago. I explained in great detail
why the current situation exists. There
was a time when Iran and Israel were
allies
during the dictatorship of of uh
Muhammad Rai the sha of Iran who was a
US asset a western asset who was selling
his country's oil reserves to the west
at deeply discounted rates and then
Muhammad Mosad the prime minister took
over and he nationalized Iran's oil
industry which is why operation Ajax
happened and the Americans got rid of
him and then the sharkam back as a
dictator and then there's the Iranian
revolution, the Islamic revolution and
they are pro Palestine. So the new
regime was pro Palestine and they said
that Israel is an is is is is a col
colonial project and so on and so forth.
Long story if you want to understand
properly watch that episode 7 of geost
strategy in which I have explained
everything in proper detail in great
detail.
Uh WRV13133 says will we ever get Axai
back as China is far stronger than us
also why don't China ally with India
India and China together will be
unstoppable
well
when you are a much stronger nation you
don't seek allies you seek vasals
that is the nature of power if you want
to understand why it is so read texts
like the earth shastra etc so then you
will understand Why China doesn't want
to ally with India? China would rather
see an India that is broken up or an
India or an India that is very weak or
an India that is a Chinese vasal. They
don't want to ally with India.
Historically we have been the far
greater civilization. But today we are a
weaker nation because of the history of
the past whatever years right few
decades few centuries and so on so
forth. Essentially the past eight
decades that's why China is about three
and a half or four times more powerful
than us today.
So why will they want India to be an
ally when they can make India
potentially a vasal, right? And India is
the one Asian nation that they fear
because they know that India still has
the potential to become the next China
in the next 15 or so years if we get our
things right. If a lot of things go
right for us.
So why would China want to align with
us? They would rather keep us down.
So then the question is will we ever get
accession back? Someday we will. History
is long. We won't get it back in the
next 5 years, 10 years, 30 years, who
knows? It's possible. 100 years very
likely. It all depends on what we do and
where we take our country. So we should
not look at the next two weeks or next 3
months or next 3 years. We are the
oldest civilization. We have a history
that goes back now I would say 12,000
years at least. So for us, what is 20
years, 50 years? What's a 100 years for
us? It's nothing. See it that way. Don't
think as a small little nation state.
Think like a civilization state. Of
course, it goes beyond our lifetimes,
but so what? Our descendants will get
it, right? So we will get it back
eventually. We'll we may get a lot more
in the future. Who knows? Who knows what
where where history will take us. So
let's not be, I would say, pessimistic.
Let's not be defeist.
things will work out and we have to make
things work out together.
Vishal says Iran launched 150 missiles
on day one, 75 on day two, 40 then, not
10, 15, 20. It's decreasing day by day.
How long can Iran save its ballistic
missile launchers? Well, it remains to
be seen. It remains to be seen. Iran may
also be signaling to the world that
look, we want to end this nonsense. We
want an end to this war. They've also
signaled like I said 50 minutes ago
they've also signaled to the US by our
various mediators like Oman and Qatar
etc etc that we would like this to end
if is if Israel stops the attacks we
will also stop the attacks so they are
signaling that they would like the war
to end right it doesn't mean that they
they it doesn't necessarily mean that
they have lost their capabilities
uh they may still have a lot of aces up
their sleeve believe
um and it is also likely that Iran has
way more ballistic missiles than Israel
has iron dome missiles. That's also a
likelihood and even the US may not be
able to u you know fill that gap
potentially.
So maybe Iran is trying to say that you
know what we are willing to deescalate
if you are willing to deescalate
and maybe if deescalation doesn't happen
then you may see a much bigger surge of
missiles coming in from Iran potentially
or maybe you are right and maybe they
their capabilities are being degraded
day by day and maybe they are becoming
more and more helpless that's also a
possibility but without us being there
we don't know so I think we have to be
cautious I don't think Iran is that that
helpless right
Aris Manticor says the opposition
parties are promoting language racism to
divide our country. Many influential
people have also started supporting this
foreign toolkit. Well, this is not
something I'm going to take today. I'm
going to take I'm not going to take
local politics. I generally never take
local politics. Right. But I would say
in answer to your to your to your uh
statement and question it's very
unfortunate and u it's very likely that
there could be a foreign influence
behind this. I think it's almost
guaranteed that there is a foreign
influence behind this and we the people
have to ensure that these forces whoever
they may be I'm not naming anybody but
whoever they may be they should not
succeed. It's for us to ensure that that
such ps, such tactics, such strategies
do not succeed.
Webhav Dangra says, "Shouldn't countries
teach correct history?" Way of dangra
seems to be in Japan.
So, shouldn't countries teach correct
history? in Tokyo Yakosuni Shine Shine
Museum. They glorify and worship the
Japanese Second World War army. There is
incorrect info information regarding
Manuria. There is no mention of unit
731.
Okay.
Shouldn't countries teach correct
history?
Well, I would say ideally everybody
should speak the only the truth. But if
you read the Artastra, you will see that
nobody speaks the truth.
So we don't live in an ideal world right
everybody is lying everybody is trying
to pedal narratives
so then as an every nation will also try
to promote its own narratives now I'm
not saying what what happened during the
second world war the conduct of the
Japanese imperial army during the second
world war was abominable no question
about it
but is it the only army that was
abominable do you have any idea of what
the other nonaccess forces did that's
never mentioned. So, shouldn't we also
ask the same question about the allies?
And if we are not asking the question
about the allies, then why are we only
asking questions about the defeated
Japanese? The Japanese were defeated.
They were smashed. They have been
colonized. They have been brutalized.
They've been enslaved. They're trying to
hold on to some shred of pride of some
kind.
Right? So I would see my point is first
of all as an Indian who lives in Japan
I would say we should respect whatever
the local people are trying to do. Okay.
We should not be judgmental
and if you want to be judgmental we
should be equally judgmental towards
everybody. What the Americans have done
on Japan they tested two nuclear weapons
on on the civilians. That's not the only
thing they have done. what they did in
Germany. What they did in Germany after
the fall of the third. Do you have any
idea what was done in Germany?
It was essentially genocide of the
Germans
in various parts of Europe. I mean
there's so many horrors that have
happened that are completely suppressed.
So shouldn't countries teach correct
history? They should. But why are we
singling out only one country? The
country that has suffer essentially
suffered more than most countries.
So yeah, theoretically you're right.
Everybody should teach correct history.
But shouldn't the US teach correct
history?
Shouldn't Europe teach correct history
of what they have done in Africa?
Shouldn't the US teach the history of
what they did in the continent they
stole from the natives?
Right? They they portray themselves as
the champions of human rights and
democracy while living on a land that
has been genocided of the natives and
where natives today even today live as
secondass citizens. That that goes for
the entirety of the Americas by the way
overall.
So the point I'm trying to make is that
nobody is going to teach correct
history. Everybody is going to tell
lies. That's the way the way of the
world at least in the current cycle of
that we're living in. Kalyuga, everybody
is going to lie.
That's just the way it is. So,
okay. Coral Jane says, "What do you
think is going to be Pakistan's role in
the Israel Iran war after Aim Munir's US
visit? Is the US going to use Pakistan's
air bases? If they do, how would the
whole situation pan out?" Well, first of
all, please understand one thing very
clearly. Pakistan is a complete 100%
certified US wasal.
Okay. Trump is deeply invested in
Pakistan personally. His empire, the
Trump business empire is deeply invested
in Pakistan. They stand a lot to gain
from Pakistan. That's why Trump has this
tremendous love for Pakistan. Now in
exchange for Trump's attentions and
benevalence towards Pakistan, Pakistan
will give whatever the US needs.
So right now one hears that there are
American u aircraft that are flying over
Pakistani territory uh looking into
what's happening in Iran.
Okay reconnaissance aircraft and
whatever u various kinds of aircraft
American aircraft are flying over
Pakistani territory. So Pakistan has
opened its airspace to the Americans. Do
whatever you want. It's all yours. We
know that the Americans have been using
the Nurhan air base and even Pakistani
officers are off limits over there. The
air base is off is off limits to
Pakistanis. It's it's controlled by the
Americans. The Nurh Khal air base. I
think that's now pretty much
known to the world, right?
Um so what could happen is the question
in this Israel Iran war. So if the US
decides in the next few days, maybe in a
week, maybe in 3 days, maybe in 30 days,
whenever they decide possibly that they
want to
launch some kind of operation on on
Iraq, which means on Iran, which means
that the US, if they decide that they
will get involved in the war, then they
they could very much use Pakistani air
bases as the staging grounds of their
air strikes or whatever, right? And if
it happens, there's nothing much Iran
can do about it. Maybe Iran can try and
hit hit Pakistani air bases. Maybe Iran
can do that. Um but if the US gets
involved, it's going to be a big big big
glo not global but regional war. If if
it is happening from Pakistan, then even
Pakistan gets dragged into the war and
Pakistan may take some damage from from
Iranian missile strikes and so on. So if
the US decides to use Pakistani air
bases in territory, then even Pakistan
will get dragged into the war. That's
how it could pan out. But if the US
decides that it's going to get involved
then it's then it's uh going to be very
bad days for Iran because the US is all
powerful as we know.
Arun says recent times now article said
that Israel wanted to strike Pakistan
nuclear site. India said no. I also
heard US made Israel stops the stop
their plans which is true. Well, we
don't know. There are multiple versions
of the story story going around right
now.
What I had heard or read back in the day
whenever it was years ago is that Israel
decided to pull out at the last moment.
Now some people are claiming that it was
the Indian prime minister Mr. Moraji
Desai who stopped Israel from using
Indian air bases or and and
denied Israel permission to to use
Indian air bases. I am not sure which
story is true but understand it from
this perspective. Pakistan has always
been a US asset for decades and Israel
and the US have the special
relationship. So the question is why
would Israel destroy u something that is
a US asset doesn't make sense right I
think there is some some kind of
understanding let's like in the episode
of geost strategy that I just concluded
today
we we saw that there was a US there was
a secret Iran alliance in the 1980s when
Saddam Hussein and Iran were fighting
and Israel was supplying Iran
with arms, ammunition, etc. despite
officially the two nations being
enemies. So I think there could be
similar situation between Israel and
Pakistan. Okay, that's what I think. I
have no evidence to back it up, but I
have historical precedents which I just
gave you that such things happen.
Um, and it is also possible that the
Americans may actually have told Israel,
don't go ahead and bob the Pakistani
nuclear facilities. We want this to be
an eyewash so that we can provide
Pakistan with our nuclear weapons and
then claim that these are Pakistani
nukes. That's also a possibility. So we
don't quite know what the real story is.
Various people will will make various
claims. But what evidence do they have
to back up the claims? I'm not sure what
evidence they have. Even I don't have
evidence to back up the claims. But I
can offer you historical precedents that
show you that things happen in the in in
such ways.
Schubam says, "Some people are praising
and glorifying Portuguese trade and
architecture, ignoring reality. 300 plus
pilgrims were burned in 1502. Goa
massacres in 1510. Two centuries of
torture and forced conversions during
the Goa Inquisition. What's my take? My
take is that the Portuguese were
barbarians. The Portuguese were utter
barbarians. They came into India. They
captured some territory. They they
violently violently oppressed the
people. They destroyed temples. They
built churches on temples. They forced
Indians to become Christians by force,
by coercion. Those Indians who refused
to become Christian even after
converting they were burned at the
stake.
Okay. They they had these these
activities called Ottoaf in which people
were burned alive because they were
secretly practicing their their
ancestral culture despite officially
becoming Christian and so on. Absolute
horror show. The the Portuguese were
utter barbarians. Their conduct was
barbaric.
And today if some people are praising
and glorifying those people they should
those people should be ashamed.
How can you glorify and praise what the
Portuguese did in India? They were their
behavior their conduct was barbaric. It
was abominable. And the people who are
praising that should be ashamed of
themselves. That's my take on that.
MK says duara is 9,500 years old. It's
mentioned in the Mahabharat. The rigveda
is older than the Mahabharat. So riged
could be over 9,500 years old. Look,
the duara, we know that duara is maybe 9
and a half thousand years old. Okay, we
have uh carbon dating evidence from a
piece of wood that goes back about 8,000
something years and it's most likely
older than that. So maybe it's 9,500
years old. Maybe it's 10,000 years old.
Duhara. Now Dara is mentioned in the
Rigveda and in the in in the Mahabharat
and in the Mahabarat it is said that
there was a major earthquake and Dara
was swallowed up by the sea during the
time of the Mahabarat.
Okay, I agree. But it is is it not
possible that Dwara may be 5,000 years
older than the Mahabharat and it was
still existing during the time of the
Mahabharat. It's possible, right?
So maybe the Mahabharat was written I'm
just giving a completely hypothetical
date. Maybe let's say the Mahabharat
happened let's say hypothetically 5,000
years ago and Dara existed then. But
maybe Darka also existed 5,000 years
before that.
And let's say the Riga we know it's
older than the Mahabarat. Maybe let's
say hypothetically the Riga is 3,000
years older than the Mahabarat. So the
Mahabharat hypothetically happened 5,000
years ago. The Rigida was written 3,000
years before that hypothetically. So the
Rigida is 8,000 years old and maybe Dara
was existed even before that possibly.
So that way the math doesn't add up. You
understand what I'm saying? So the
rigida could possibly be over 9,500
years old or maybe it's younger than
that. We don't know. We don't know for
sure. The clearest way of dating the
Riga is by looking at the evidence of
the Saraswati.
We know at what point in time the
Sarasati was at her peak. We know at
what point in time the Sarasati started
declining slowly as a river. We know at
what point in time the Sarasati dried
out to a large extent. And the Rida
mentioned the Sarasati as a river in her
prime. And the Sarasati was last in her
prime around 6,000 BC. That's around
8,000 years to ago. So it indicates the
rigida is more likely to have been
written around 6,000 BC than around 1500
BC. That is the best estimate I can give
you. Beyond that, I can't say until we
find further evidence of some kind.
Yesh, are we heading towards World War
II, 1919, Spanish flu, 1929, Great
Depression, 1939, World War II, World
War II now? The same thing happens.
COVID recession, World War II, so many
wars happening. Well, maybe, maybe not.
I hope not. It is not necessary that the
pattern that happened 100 days ago has
to exactly happen in the same way this
time.
Maybe it will happen in a different way
this time this this time around. So the
pattern you saw in the beginning of the
of the 20th century there is no reason
for it to occur exactly in the same
sequence, same order and same magnitude
all over again.
History is cyclical but it's not a
carbon copy of what happened in the
past.
So one hopes that it doesn't go in that
direction. I know there are lots of wars
happening. We are we are in a in a
period of geopolitical instability. It's
it's getting worse, but hopefully
there's no world war. We've had the the
the COVID which was terrible. Uh so the
pattern seems to be there, but hopefully
it doesn't occur exactly the same way as
before. That's what I would say. It's
not guaranteed that it will happen that
way. But yeah, it's kind of concerning.
So I agree with you. It's concerning.
Only gems says which countries would be
part of a bhat.
It's up to you. Entirely up to you.
Historically Akandarat was jammudep the
whole of the subcontinent south of the
Himalayas plus Gandhar and all and so
on. Historically our boundaries the
India central Asia boundary was at the
gates at a certain gate
in Tajakistan.
Yeah, that's so when Chingis Khan
crossed that gate, he was in India which
was currently about 100 kilometers
inside Tajakistan and so on. So India
had a huge huge huge sphere of
influence. Um geographically it was
Jambodep. So we would have Afghanistan,
Pakistan is part of it also uh Nepal uh
present day Bangladesh and the Ca
regions which is Sri Lanka, Maldi etc
and so on. And civilizationally we went
much beyond that which is the whole of
the sword Nabumi Southeast Asia and so
on so forth. So it's up to it's open to
interpretation but I think the
subcontinent was akalat mainly the
subcontinent.
Go says uh today prime minister Modi
said Trump did not immediate ceasefire
to which Trump replied he did. How
should Modi respond? Now Mr. Modi should
ignore this nonsense from the honorable
president of the United States Shri
Donald Trump. There's no point engaging
in this verbal slinging tit for tat
thing. Trump is blatantly lying. He also
lied today that Mr. Modi was just just
now in the White House before Mr. Munir
was there. Trump Mr. Trump is known to
to to to
preicate. So Mr. Modi should not respond
to Mr. Trump.
Geopolitical Dubet says, "Did the Gupta
Empire start building grand temples?"
I'm not sure what the grand see the
problem with the grand temples that we
have. All all are in ruins. The problem
is that we don't know how to date them.
You can't carbon date rock. Rock is
inorganic, right? The problem is we
can't carbon date rocks.
So, I'm not sure how these so-called
historians and archaeologists assign
various dates to the temples. For
example, in in Egypt, if you look at the
pyramids, if you look at the Sphinx, the
Sphinx is clearly way older than the
pyramids. And yet they say it was built
around so- and so date. So these people,
they come out with these dates, they
they pull the dates out of a hat, it
looks like. So we don't know when we
started building the grand temples. It's
possible that many of our grand temples
are way older than what historians
claim. For example, the Padvanabas Swami
temple in Kerala,
it has coins that date back far far
before the temple is supposed to be
built and so on. So I'm not sure when we
started building grand temples. We've
always had great dynasties, great
kingdoms and empires in this country
that go back way beyond the the um Nanda
Empire way before the Nanda Empire. We
have all these lineages recorded, you
know, in our history text. Some of them
survive but these are not mapped one to
one with various uh uh archaeological
sites because we kind of have lost uh
that continuity. So it's possible that
grand temples were being built way
before the Gupta Empire. It's possible.
One example is is Kaneshka. Kaneshka
built a grand stupa which kind of still
exists in Peshawar today but it's today
a slum. There's a slum on top of it and
so on. So it's possible that grand
temples were being built before the
Guptas also. But classically they say
that it's the Guptas who began this
great uh practice of building great
temples which I I find hard to believe
it. I'm sure it was being done before
the Guptas also. So I really don't know
for sure.
Rahul says large Shia Muslims in India
trace their roots to ancient migrations
from Syria, Lebanon, Iran. Um, backed by
history, genetics confirm liantine haplo
groups absent in non-Muslims but present
in Shia Muslims. Forgotten history. Uh,
it's possible. Look, people forget
history especially when it's not written
down. Especially when your records are
destroyed or whatever. For example, do
most people today know who their great
great-grandfather was? Who one of the
great great grandmothers know
grandmothers was? Do you know the names?
It's so easy to forget history. And if
you've been in India for let's say 700
years, 800 years, even 500 years, you
kind of, you know, the the origins are
lost in time. They become kind of
legends or even myths. Uh but yeah,
genetics is good in bringing these
things out. So maybe it's forgotten
history. U Syria, Lebanon, Iran, even
Yemen, even Yemen has, you know, some
some kind of there is some Yemenist
component also in various Shia Muslim
groups in India.
So it's it's part of history. It's it's
it's part of how things go. People go
back and forth, back and forth. There is
no one, you know, a single line of
migration or whatever. It's always waves
and waves and back and forth, back of
mouth, migration and so on. Especially
when you have a gigantic place like this
Indian subcontinent which is so rich and
capable of of of sustaining gigantic
population. You'll have people coming in
all the time and settling down. So not
surprising but clearly forgotten
history. So yeah, you're right.
Okay, I'm going to do another 15 minutes
and then we're done. Right. Tip says
Kiev was a Viking state. How did the
Slavs bounce back? Well, that's a long
history. You'll have to go into the
history of the Kiev and Roose. The the
leaders were were Vikings, of course,
but the people were Slavic and
eventually the Slavs just they were just
larger in number numerically and so on.
And that's how so the Slavs were not
colonized by the Vikings but they had a
um it's kind of you know it was kind of
like uh the Mitani kingdom the Mitani
kingdom mitani empire was an Indo-arian
arian Indian origin Arian superstrait
over a local Hurian population. So the
royalty was Indian Indo-arian they spoke
Sanskrit but the people were the Hurian
people who spoke the Hurian language but
the empire was of Indo-Aryan origin but
eventually today there's no Arian
language being spoken in the region in
Syria in in in
um the Anatolia region where the Bitani
Empire used to exist. So the people
there would still today have a little
bit of Indian ancestry but nobody will
know about it. So that's how eventually
you know the superstrates they dissolve
into the population and then the
population its cultural identity takes
over. So that's I suppose how it
happened uh for for KV the kavan roose
shaspbat says how might global society
have evolved differently if a universal
language like espiranto had achieved the
worldwide adoption and integration I
have no idea. I've been hearing about
espiranto since I was a kid. It's an
artificial language similar to various
European languages made up and some
people speak it. I don't know what's the
purpose of it. It's completely
artificial, completely made up. And
Espiranto means hopeful or something.
But what difference does it make? And
why would somebody adopt a foreign
language? We, for example, let me tell
you, we in India have language have a
civilizational history that goes back
10, 12, 15, god knows how many thousands
of years. We have our own languages
which are the oldest languages in the
world. Why would we accept a foreign
madeup artificial language? Why? Why?
Makes no sense. And why do we need
worldwide adoption and integration? Why
do we need the whole society to speak
just one language and become a
monoculture of sorts? Why? The world is
beautiful because of genuine diversity,
regional diversity. We don't want all
the diversity to be in one place. We
want that when we travel to different
places, we find different cultures,
different languages, different ways of
life. That's what makes the world
beautiful. If we impose just one
language, one culture on the whole
thing, it makes the world ugly.
So I am not in a favor of aspiranto or
whatever. I've never understood it its
import, its purpose, its meaning. Kind
of a delusional kind of thing to do like
uh
what was his name? like the guy who
wrote the book utopia during the time of
uh Henry VIII
more Thomas Moore utopia there's no such
thing as utopia in the world
okay Gorav Singh says what's the origin
of the Rajput people of India and is
their lineage the same as the chhatrias
from the past similar to how the
Brahmans have a continuous lineage
please do an episode of it on it if
possible
an episode will be okay but I can answer
the question Look a thousand years ago
in the in the year 1,000 AD
nobody called themselves Rajuts. Nobody
did. The word did not exist. Then
eventually this term called Rajautra
came into existence and that's the
origin of the word Rajaput. So who are
the Rajaputras? They are the descendants
of the original dynasties of India, the
royal dynasties, royal clans.
And according to various authors and
sources, there were about 33 royal uh
dynasties in India dating back to post
rigidic times dating back to the Vic
age. So these dynasties have been around
in India for thousands of years and uh
33 in number apparently and the the the
descendants of those dynasties, the
descendants of the old royalty, they
called themselves the Rajautras and they
were at the forefront of fighting the
Turk uh invasions of India and they
fought for several centuries and
eventually others took up the good fight
eventually later like the Maratas and so
on so forth.
So the origin of the Rajput people is
the origin of all the people of India
but they were the aristocracy the
royalty. So they were warriors of course
but their lineage is not necessarily the
same as the other chhatrias. The
chhatrias are the the warrior class of
India. They were the people engaged in
warfare but they were not necessarily
the descendants of kings so on. So we
all have a continuous lineage. All of
us, no matter what your lineage is,
whatever your u cast so-called cast is,
we all have lineages going back tens of
thousands of years. Okay? So, it's not
just that the Rajputs or so and so or
the brahinss or whoever has ancient
lineages. We all have tremendously
ancient lineages. We are the oldest
non-African population on the surface of
the planet and we are all essentially
the same people genetically. Okay,
that's what we remember.
Geopolitical Dubai. Thank you so much
sir. Thank you. Very kind of you. Uh
Arun says why countries like Thailand,
Cambodia and many Southeast Asian
countries don't hate the Chola invaders
from outside. Usually the the people who
are invaded hate their invaders.
Well, the Chola invasion was a one-off
event. The thing is this. See, we have
to understand this one thing and get it
very clear. It was not the Chola
invasion of Shri Vijaya that brought
Hinduism and Sanskrit into Southeast
Asia into Sward Napi. That's not the
case.
The Indianization
of the whole of Southeast Asia began at
least 3,000 years ago. It began with the
voyages of the great merchants from
Kolinga across the sea of Kolinga today
called the Bay of Bengal into
Subarabumi. That's Thailand, Indonesia,
Cambodia and so on so forth. All of that
and this happened over centuries over
thousands of years and slowly these
regions the people of these regions they
absorbed Indian culture, Indian
religion, Indian language and they all
became Indianized. The first ever
Cambodian kingdom was the kingdom of
Funan and they that kingdom was founded
by a a Cambodian princess and she
married an Indian
uh merchant called Condinia. So they
were the founders of the Funan kingdom
which eventually became today's Cambodia
and so on. So all of these different
regions, the whole of Southeast Asia,
all the different cultures there, they
all eventually over centuries became
Indianized and the Indianization did not
happen through force. They just absorbed
our culture because they saw it as
possibly superior to what whatever
lifestyle and culture they had. So they
slowly slowly absorbed our culture and
they they built such incredible
beautiful temples. Ankorwat my god uh
prammanan in Indonesia the various Shiva
temples in in the Cham Champa region the
Priya Vihar temple for which Cambodia
and Thailand are still fighting and so
on which is a shiva temple. So the
Indianization Hinduization all of that
happened over centuries over millennia.
It was never done by force. The local
people local cultures absorbed this
willingly and they synchretatized it
with their own culture. So wherever you
go in Southeast Asia, wherever Hinduism
still exists, it eventually became
Buddhism. But same thing. So it's a very
syncretive kind of culture with lots of
indigenous elements, ancestral elements
synretized with Indian civilization and
culture. The Chola invasion was a
one-off thing. It was a it was a
geopolitical event. And once again, it
was not an oppressive event. We did not
go and enslave people, massacre people,
and all that. It was just that's a whole
different story. So yeah, that's why
there is no hate for Indians or chasers.
Absolutely none. Because we were never
oppressive. We were never colonizers. We
were never extractive.
We we never enslaved anybody. We never
stole people's wealth. We enriched them
actually. That's how it was. Yeah.
That's why there's no hatred.
Wamshi Kalam says no. Bahalika kingdom
of Bashma Empire. Bashma
uncle and Capisa in Afghanistan.
Bahalik. Yeah, it's today that region is
called Balk today. Bahalik and Capisa.
Capisa is is Kabul. I suppose the names
changed eventually. Pushawati. Pushawati
became Peshawar. Pushawati was also
known as Purushpur and then it became
Peshawar. Bahalika became Balk. Uh
Capisa became the Kabul region and so
on. And of course this is Gandhar. So um
the the that element of the Korova
people
um the the maternal ancestry of the kora
was from was from Gandhar obviously
right today's Afghanistan and so on
uh the rational reporter says is it
possible if Iran falls then Pakistan
loses utility for the US the US shifts
full-time focus on China starts causing
up with India Pakistan neglected and
effed up well I would love to see
Pakistan effed up But that's not the
case. See, let's say Iran falls.
Hypothetically, we don't want that to
happen because it's terrible. But let's
say Iran falls. Then will Pakistan lose
utility for the US? My dear friends, as
long as India exists, Pakistan is very
useful for the US. Very useful. The US
wants two things for Pakistan. First of
all, Pakistan should no longer go and
get into bed with China.
Secondly, Pakistan should continue to
destabilize India permanently. Then how
can Pakistan ever lose utility? Iran is
a shi sideh show. Iran is a sideesh
show. India and China are the big deal.
Right now India is useful for the US
against China. That's why they want
India and China to remain enemies. But
eventually India is also a problem for
the US. The US doesn't want any new
poles emerging anywhere. So Pakistan is
not going to lose its utility. Not going
to happen.
Um, Lkesh Singh says, "Do you know about
the breakthrough in quantum computing
from DRDO IIT Delhi? I heard that
they've achieved some kind of
breakthrough in quantum entanglement.
Quantum entanglement has been sustained
over a distance of more than a
kilometer. That's fantastic. Great job.
It's a good breakthrough. It's good
progress. We want quantum entanglement
to happen over hundreds of kilometers.
So why shouldn't why doesn't India
launch its own version of the micious
satellite? Chinese have launched one and
they were able to entangle a pair of of
particles, photons or whatever it was
between the satellite and a ground
station in China.
So I I think it's great. I'm aware of
it. I've not looked into the details but
I've heard the news that we have done we
have entangled a pair of particles
a single quantum system over a distance
of more than a kilometer apparently. So
good good progress. Keep on going keep
on going. Extend it to 10 kilometers and
100 kilometers. Then let's extend it to
the Andromea galaxy.
It's possible.
Rishik says, "Hey Chava, hey Chava, did
foreign powers ever try to sabotage
India's nuclear program?" Well, I have
not been a part of the Indian nuclear
program, so I can't say that. But it's
very likely that foreign powers have
tried to do that. It makes sense. If of
all the nuclear programs that exist on
the planet, which are the ones? The US
was the original nuclear program? The
Manhattan project. Then the Russians got
some info from there from the Manhattan
project via various sources and they did
their own nuclear program through that.
Then you have the British, the French
who all were helped by the US. Then you
had the Chinese who were helped by
Russia. Then you had Iran. Then you had
Israel and South South Africa also for
for a while that also got knowhow from
the US and other other allied nations.
It was only India that developed a
nuclear program entirely independently
without any foreign help.
And of course it is guaranteed that
foreign powers would have tried to
sabotage the nuclear program. Maybe it's
still ongoing but the details will not
come out because this a very classified
kind of information very highly
sensitive information and the details
won't come out. So don't know.
N says as per physicists neutrino
neutrino can travel a light year thick
wall of steel without interaction. So
why are nutrinos not considered dark
matter? Well because we can detect them.
Neutrinos are not considered to be dark
matter because we can still detect them.
We have these gigantic nutrino detectors
deep underground in Japan super kamio
and wherever else that can detect a few
nutrinos in a year. solar neutrinos.
Okay. So that's why because they
interact via the weak interaction
and they do occasionally interact with
electromagnetic matter like heavy water
or whatever. That's why we are able to
detect this through scintillation
centilation technology and whatever
else. And that's why it's not dark
matter. The question is what is dark
matter? Dark matter is that mysterious
unknown matter that affects the rotation
curves of galaxies.
So when you see the speed at which
galaxies rotating, we can see the speed
at which galaxy galaxy rotating. How do
how can we see that? I mean if you look
at a galaxy it's not moving right but we
still know that the galaxies are
rotating because of the red shift and
blue shift of the stars at the two ends
of the galaxy. So we can know which
direction the galaxy is rotating in in
and at what speed it's rotating. Now if
you plot that against the expected speed
of rotation, you'll find that galaxies
are rotating at a very different speed
as if they have 10 times the mass
and that's the hidden matter that was
discovered through galaxy rotation
curves. Dark matter which is not
neutrino matter. It is something else
entirely. It seems to interact only
gravitationally. It doesn't have the
weak interaction, the strong interaction
or the electromagnetic interaction. It
seems to have only the gravitational
interaction. It's a different class of
matter. It's not neutrinos. So you could
argue that neutrinos are also some kind
of undetectable largely undetectable
particle. But that's not what is causing
the galaxies to rotate in a different
way. It's not neutrinos. It's something
else. And that's the dark matter we are
looking for.
Hardik says North Korea is also testing
missiles. The problem is that you close
your eyes and point anywhere on the map
and a war is happening. It's on the
rise. What are my thoughts? It's all
interconnected.
The world is bifurcating. there's a
visible ongoing bifurcation of the world
order maybe triurcation mainly mainly
bifurcation so it's the western order
the US-led order versus the Russia China
order and part of the Russia China
coalition you have Iran you have North
Korea
that's about it more or less so North
Korea also wants to ensure that nobody
comes and you know tries to do what what
is being done to Iran right now. So
North Korea first of all they have
nuclear weapons a decent quantity
perhaps of nuclear weapons we don't know
what the number is but decent quantity
and they have the missiles to deliver
the nuclear weapons so they are
continuously testing the missiles and
reminding the world don't mess with us
and that's a signal to the world uh
especially the west so that's the deal
right now there are wars happening at
the place in other places there's there
are conflicts happening in Africa
nobody's paying attention to them I mean
tremendous amounts of people are being
displaced There's a horrific horrific
humanitarian catastrophe going on in Sud
Sudan right now where the government and
the other forces are fighting each other
and the civilians are caught in the
crossfire deliberately perhaps and so
on. So the world is has entered a period
of great geopolitical instability. It's
because of the rise of new powers and
the rise of powers that are still not
great powers but that that naturally
will rise like India and so on and there
are existing powers that don't want this
to happen. So there's tremendous churn
happening in the world. So that's the
deal and this is going to intensify
unfortunately that's the direction in
which the world is going. Intensified
instability.
MK says what what lessons did the US
learn from the UK's fall as an empire?
The UK never fell as an empire. The
entity still continues in the form of
the US. There was just a transfer of
power from Washington from London to
Washington. The UK never fell. And of
course you can learn some lessons from
the UK's followers and empire. The UK
was too small. The UK was see the
problem of the UK is that it's it's a
small island and it's very close to
traditional enemies like like like
France, like Germany, it's very it's in
very close proximity to these enemies.
So it's always under threat no matter
how powerful it is because if you strike
at London, if you strike at the
heartland, then the whole empire can
collapse like a pack of cards. So what
lesson did the US learn? be far away
from your en enemies. So look at the
map. Look at the map. Okay, I'll show
you the map. The US has ensured it is
completely isolated from the enemies. If
you look at the map, the US is
surrounded on two sides by gigantic
oceans, the Atlantic and the Pacific.
And it has ensured that all the nations
in the Americas are their vasals. And
they pose no threat whatsoever to the
US. So the Americans have learned their
lessons very well.
Okay,
Kumar Kaneska says, "Fascinated about
dark matter and dark energy. Could you
suggest where to read about and learn
about it? Miss your science episodes.
Please do it once a month, please."
Okay. Well, I would love to do it, but
nobody watches. Nobody watches. Nobody
cares. I would love to talk about
science every day. But nobody watches. I
mean, I've got this live stream going
on, a recorded live stream on Loop
playing about science, about the science
episodes. I mean, I typically see
there's one or two people watching it.
There's no interest. What can I do about
it? Um, how to read and learn about dark
matter and dark energy? Well, I don't
know. Uh,
um, popular science books I would have
to recommend, right? Um, I Okay, let me
tell you. I think I have
I think one of the first videos I ever
did was a recommendation video about
books. Let me see. So, this is my
channel. Let's go to the oldest videos
and look at these goofy videos that I
made here. So, here's a video 14 or so
minutes long books for understanding
quantum theory and dark matter. I think
you should look at this video. In this
video, I must have recommended some
reasonably good books. Hopefully, not
very technical books, but uh books that
most people could hopefully understand.
So, I think if you look at that video,
you should get some answers. But off the
top of my head, I don't know any any
popular science books about dark matter,
dark energy because I don't really read
popular science books. So I don't know.
Um yeah, so please check out that video.
Hopefully you get answers from answers
from that.
And Ankita G, thank you so much. Really
appreciate that. Not asking a question
but you. So thank you. Thank you for
that.
Okay. Rohan says, can the Indian private
sector make world-class weapons? The
answer in very short and very brief is
100% yes. We saw some of that during
operation sindur. W absolutely saw that.
So the answer is very much yes. We can.
Sam the gamer says, "What geopolitical
threat does a pro- US puppet Iran pose
for India? What key strategic benefits
or perks do would we lose? Love the geo
strategy show." Well, I'm glad you love
it. And if you watch episode seven of
geost strategy that I did just before
this episode, you will have all the
answers in that. So I'll tell you what
briefly.
If you have a puppet government in Iran,
which is a US puppet government, then it
becomes like an extension of Pakistan.
So right now you have Iran that is
allied with China and Russia and it has
good relations with with India. It
doesn't do anything that would be
detrimental to Indian interests overall,
right? and it's not a great friend of ch
of of Pakistan. India, Iran and Pakistan
don't have good relations. I promise you
that. So it kind of keeps Pakistan also
balanced out. Now if you have a pro- US
government in Iran, it goes back to the
1960s when Iran was very very
anti-India. Iran supported Pakistan
during the 1965 war against India and so
on. So you will have an India that is
increasingly isolated in the region and
that is terrible uh for us.
So that's the short answer. If you want
the proper detailed answer, watch out,
watch episode 7 of geost strategy.
Anyhow, thank you so much.
Okay, Galler, thank you. First of all,
the question is, how long will embedded
C be a relevant skill set? For your
information, one of the one of the few
software development areas precluded
from AI gluttony,
for example, open WRT tomato. Okay.
How long will embedded C be a relevant
skill set? Embedded C and that's not
something I have come I have really
worked on during my time in the IT
industry. I have obviously used C in the
past but I use it in the in the sense of
using it for physics purposes. Physics
I'm not sure about embedded C.
I'm not sure not sure. Um, one of the
few software development areas precluded
from AI gluttony. OpenWRT tomato.
Uh, let me try and Google this tomato.
Open tomato and embedded C. What is
that? Maybe that'll give me some clues.
Okay. Embedded seed tomato
tomato.com.
Okay. So, I'm not familiar with this
stuff. Clearly, I have not been using
any of this. Um, if I do use any
programming today, I would typically use
Python. So, I'm I'm I'm sorry. I'm not
aware
of the context and I'm not aware of of
the of of of
embedded sea and tomato and all that.
So, I'm sorry I'm not able to answer
your question, but I think yeah,
Gluttony will eventually take over
everything. That's what I'm seeing. I
mean no matter what uh whether it is
NodeJS, whether it is C++, whether it is
Java, whether it is Python, AI does
everything.
So I don't know, maybe it's a matter of
time if it is still not part of the AI
gluttony. I would imagine.
Um Arun says, "Iran getting nukes good
or bad for India?" I would say not very
good. We don't want more nuclear powers
in the region, but I would very much
want Iran to remain a sovereign nation
the way it is right now and not become a
US puppet, one more US puppet in the
region. But yeah, I would not be very
pleased with Iran getting nukes.
Goind says, do you think if Biden was
president, he would have supported
Israel with the same intensity as Trump
is doing currently? I think Biden would
have supported Israel, but maybe perhaps
not with the same intensity that that
Trump is doing, or maybe perhaps with
more intensity. The thing is that the
thing is that it doesn't matter who is
the US president. They always support
Israel, whoever it is. So it makes no
real difference. So I think it would not
really make much of a difference.
Uh Wooden Armor says in your TRS
podcast, you mentioned the Indian IT
industry would collapse soon. As someone
who was just starting out my career in
IT, what's your advice? Should I
transition fields or continue learning
AI tools? the majority of the Indian ID
industry could collapse because AI will
take over all those low-level jobs all
the programming testing etc jobs but if
you upskill
in such a way that you can use AI
as a manager would use
resources coders programmers then you
would do well in AI in in IT so it will
continue the Indian IT industry the way
it is constructed the way it is
architected it's all about labor
arbitrage right in the US a programmers
programmer will charge x amounts of
dollars x amount of dollars per hour in
India we can charge one/ird of that so
that's why the US companies will
outsource to India but now because of AI
sitting in the US I will not need to
hire any employees I will just have you
know get AI agents to do the work for me
that that Indian or other programmers
would do at a fraction of the cost that
even Indian programmers would charge.
That's the problem we are facing today.
And that's why the Indian IT industry
could collapse unless they they they
somehow drastically change uh their
their their business models and so on.
So if you're just starting out your
career in IT
uh it depends what you want to do. you
want to be you want to be a programmer
or you want to be an employee in some
big corporation in which case your job
job could be very very much under threat
but if you want to be an entrepreneur
for example or if you want to be
somebody who is skilled in AI itself
such that you can be the manager the the
project manager who who handles AI agent
employees then you will do well so
that's that's what I have to say to you
but overall if the typical Indian person
who gets into the IT field typically
wants to have a long career as a
climbing the corporate ladder. You start
at the bottom ladder, bottom level as a
programmer or a QR tester or something
then you slowly slowly become a team
leader then a project leader then a
project manager then a delivery manager
and so on so forth but that is a process
that takes many many years and by that
many years have passed AI will have
transformed everything. So I think the
IT field is right now in a you know in a
in a period of great transition and if
you're at the bottom levels you will be
it's very likely unfortunately that you
might be made redundant. So my advice is
that if you want to remain in IT if you
want to be in IT you have to become AI
native you have to become somebody who
who is AI first and if you can find find
a way of doing that I think you will do
fine.
PRLTP says how RIIA and CFR
its branches are able to effectively
manage foreign policy while we fail to
manage our policy completely. Now what
is R I A and CFR?
I I don't know let me let me Google
that.
What is R I A R I I A
Royal Institute of International Affairs
Chadam House.
What is CFR? Council for Foreign
Research.
They're not managing foreign policy.
They are tools
of narrative building and so on. They're
not managing anybody's foreign policy.
They are tools in somebody's toolkit.
Of course, they are they are tools in in
in creating narratives and propagating
narrative. They're essentially
propaganda tools.
And these are ancient weapons that have
evolved over time. And we have not done
this. So we also need to invest in these
institutions and things and learn from
our adversaries. Yes.
Okay. I think we need to stop now. I
still have so many super chats to get
through. Please stop. I'll try and churn
through the super chats and then I'll be
done. Vivik says during Orurange Z's
rule Maharaja Raj Raj Singh and Shivaji
formed an alliance against Mughals
but the nextg couldn't continue the
alliance. Why? So look I am not a
specialist. I have I have not studied
Mughal history and Marata history and
all that. I don't know. The Indian
history I am interested in that
fascinates me is ancient Indian history.
The the politics of the Mughal Turk
occupation of India is depressing and
that's why I've never bothered to study
it. So I don't know I don't know what
happened in what year and who who allied
with whom and what happened the next
generation. I'm not really sure. I'm
sorry.
Um Sarang says what's next for India and
Canada? India versus Canada. What about
Kalistthan? Looks like there are good
signs. Prime Minister Carney has shown
encouraging signs of wanting to have
better relations within India. And uh
the Kalistthanis wanted to do sabotage
Mr. Modi's trip to Canada but did not
work out for them. So looks like we are
on a on a good path possibly. We'll have
to wait and watch. We can certainly
trust but we'll have to verify. Canada
has a long track record of supporting
Kalistan and being anti-India. Maybe Mr.
Carney has good intentions. So let's
see. Looks like things are better
compared to when Mr. Tudau was in
charge.
But I would not expect the support for
the Kalistthan thing to go with it
rapidly. It's a very big asset that they
have cultivated over decades and they
will not give it up that easily. So I
think it will remain behind the scenes
for now. Maybe it'll be brought out
again whenever required but as of now
things are okay. the the past few days
that we've seen but it's too early to
make any to to to jump to any
conclusions I would say too early
anime says given our low education
spending and poor infrastructure in most
institutions is re raising the budget
the first step to reform we have the
talent how do we begin to harness it
effectively if you want to reform
education educational institutions
raising the budget will make no
difference it will make no difference
you will be wasting more money into the
same snake pits
Okay. So raising the budget is not the
not the step to reform. You have to
think it through properly. And I will
not get into the details. I have various
episodes that I've dedicated to
education. If you want to see the
episodes I will tell you what episodes
they are in which I've spoken about this
in great depth in great detail multiple
episodes in which I have spoken about
education. Let's go let me show you
which which those are. I think 28.
So ask 28, 30 and 31. Uh the answers you
will find in there. What needs to be
done about the education system? What
kind of reforms need to be done?
Spending more money without changing the
structure, architecture and quality is
going to be a complete waste of money.
Uh geopolitical Dubai says, "Any
thoughts on British king Charles Third?"
No thoughts about him. I don't know.
He's just another king. Um
yeah, I I really haven't given much
thought to him. It makes no difference
really. His mom was in charge, now he's
in charge. In charge of what? I'm not
really sure. Um so yeah, no thoughts as
such. No thoughts.
Web of Dangra says about the Japanese
question. You're right. The correct
history is always hidden from the
masses. Top players are only showing us
what they want to show us. And and this
is some it's a pattern you will see all
across the world. Even in India, our
history is hidden from us. Right? In
India, all these textbooks, all these
professors, universities, colleges, they
all teach fake history. It's it's a big
project that started in the 1800s and
it's still ongoing. And you will see the
same thing all over the world.
History is is a form of narrative and
propaganda. So, yeah, that's the way
things are. Unfortunately, it would be
nice if true history was taught, but
it's not the case.
Prattab VGM says, "Will China and Russia
throw their weight behind Iran if ground
invasion? If there's a ground invasion,
I think there's very little Russia or
China can do
to stop the ground invasion.
So what Russia and China can do,
especially Russia, is they can try to
mediate and prevent a ground invasion of
Iran. But if the US decides there should
be a ground invasion, first of all, they
will have to spend several weeks and
months assembling the armed forces, the
army and the components of the ground
invasion, only then can a ground
invasion be launched. It's not that
easy. You need all the components in
place. So if you look at the invasion of
Iraq in 1991, the Americans spent
several months building up the coalition
and putting all the pieces in place
before the invasion. Even in 2003,
something similar happened. Um so it's
not that easy to just suddenly launch a
ground invasion. It can't happen that
way. But if they do that then if they
start putting the pieces in place then
Russia and China will have some time a
certain window of time to make it
difficult for the Americans to to carry
forward the ground invasion. But if the
invasion is actually launched I don't
think Russia can come in the way or
China can come in the way won't be
possible.
Uh Vidi says can't bat empower Balo and
build new park internally. How
Balojasthan is over there. How do we
empower the Baloan build a new park
internally? We don't want to build a new
Pak Pakistan internally in India. By the
way, no thank you. That's the last thing
we want to do. We may have a Pakistan in
India. Actually, so many Pakistanis have
apparently been living in India for
decades and all. So if you want to
empower Baluchistan, it will have to be
done in a very different way, in a very
subtle way. Maybe Iran can be involved,
maybe Afghanistan can be involved if
possible. Maybe not. Otherwise, we can
use our own ways of doing it. But uh
yeah,
Arada says are illegal immigrants
all illegal immigrants will be again
converted in Europe. I have no idea. I
am
Aries Manticor says we should start
should we start using AI to study our
own indigenous biology and create an
effective nutrition plant medicine
tailored to the Indian subcontinent.
That's a good idea, right? If you can
have an indigenous AI system and uh give
it access to a data set of let's say
10,000 Indian genomes that sort of thing
then it would be a very powerful tool to
have that will tell us what are the
potential genetic problems we face what
kind of nutrition is best for us and so
on so forth that's a great idea and it
makes a lot of sense
uh Milin says is the deep state involved
in illegal immigration in the U in the
EU I would say yes if you if you when
you said deep state you mean the US I'm
sure the US is behind the illegal
immigration in the EU to destabilize the
EU and make it make sure that it doesn't
become a threat again long-term like in
the future like you had in the past the
marching boots the Hugo boss reforms
Bhavy Basar thank you so much sir and
Bhavi Baskar has another question do you
what's your view on the debate of
Chanaki and cautilia being different is
there any proof stating them to be the
same indologists have debating this.
Well, I haven't come across this debate.
This is the good old story in India. Try
and break everything apart. Try and
deconstruct everything. Try and raise
questions about history. Now, Chinaki
and Kotilia are different people.
Really? I haven't heard about this. I'm
sorry.
I mean, Vasuv
and Krishna and Gopal, we have multiple
um names. No, Vasuv was not Krishna.
Obviously, Vasuv was the dad. But we
have so many names for for Krishna. We
have so many names for Arjuna. We have
so many names historically for all great
people, right? Who was Gudake? Gurudake
was Arjun. So now we will people start
claiming that Gurudakkesh and Arjun were
different entities, different people.
That's what people can do. I mean that's
what leftists do to to try to to try and
create chaos in India's histography and
so on. Well,
ICBM says why did India seals assumption
island deal fail? Because of foreign
interference because seals is an
important strategic location. If India
has
a base there, naval base or or
surveillance bra base it is good for
India and then the west doesn't like it.
The US doesn't like it. So the
assumption island deal failed because of
western interference and that's why we
have other deals. It's because of
foreign interference.
Dir Kamat says, "Do Indian national and
the Dharmic civilizational interests
really align? Why shouldn't Hindus
welcome Ayad's fall as a blow to
political Islamism?" Look, I will not go
into this question again. Uh if you want
to understand, if you want to look at
geopolitics from a narrow his religious
perspective, then you will not
understand geopolitics.
What can I say to you? You you can view
it whichever way you want. I can stop
you.
But the Iran matter is not to be looked
the Afghanistan matter is not to be
looked at from a religious perspective.
So my point is look if you want to
really understand things watch my
geostrategy episode that I did before
this live stream. If you have the time
to watch it watch it properly you will
understand something hopefully. Um
because if the ayatas fall then you will
have a pro- US government there which is
the same as a much larger Pakistan and
then later on people will cry
that India has let let everything fall
apart
there another another loss for India
that sort of thing it's a very narrow
perspective to look at everything from
just a religious perspective
of course I agree that the ayatas have
no love for us
But they don't they aren't the kind of
enemies they aren't enemies for us. They
don't have any the Taliban has no love
for India but they have no hatred for
India either. They hate Pakistan.
Similarly, India Iran has no love for
India as such.
Especially the the the government but
they don't have any hatred for India the
way Pakistan does. Understand things.
There are there are nuances in the
world. You have to understand you have
to learn to understand nuances. And the
big question is do Indian national and
dharmic civilizational interests really
align? Well, today India is a nation
state. India is not a civilization state
or a dharmic state. So the Indian nation
state is actually very often aligned
against our civilizational interests. So
that's a good question you're raising
and I gave you the answer.
Ada says, I've heard of block I've heard
the black box the flight recorder of the
Boeing is being sent to the US. I'm sure
they'll say it's the pilot's fault. The
moment you give it away to the US, well,
you've lost control of what happens.
Why can't we decode the flight recorder
and whatever the cockpit voice recorder,
the digital flight recorder? Why can't
we decode it on our own? I'm sure Boeing
is placing various firewalls and APIs
and stuff in there, but we should have
the ability to decode it on our own. If
we send it to the to a foreign country
which essentially acts like an
adversary, we will never get to the end
of what happened. It's it's unfortunate.
Uh Sam says Brazil, where does it stand
on the geopolitical chess board?
Brazil is not geopolitically very
important. It's a very big nation,
resourcerich nation. But geopolitically,
if you look at the hard power, not
significant unfortunately for Brazil.
Um Rashi Kudin says if the US gets
involved in the Middle East war, what's
the what's the outcome? Well, if the US
does get involved, they will want to
effect regime change. Then the likely
outcome will be regime change in Thran.
Yeah. So how would they get involved?
They would want to give Netanyahu a
victory. A victory could be the smallest
victory Netanyahu can get which can be
considered a victory is a proper
destruction is the proper destruction of
the Iranian nuclear program. That's the
minimum victory that Netanyahu will will
seek. Otherwise, he has not won
anything. It's been a waste of time. So,
if the US gets involved, one thing they
could do is they could uh destroy the
the the the
Iranian nuclear facility that's under
the mountain.
Okay.
That's one thing they could do. Maybe
that's enough for them. In that case,
there is no regime change. But if they
decide it's not enough, then they will
want a regime change in Iran. So these
are the two outcomes I can think of.
Either a complete destruction of Iran's
nuclear program or a step beyond is a
regime change which will be much much
much more difficult to actually do.
Okay, we are at the end finally of
today's live stream. It's gone beyond
uh
the time limit that I had for myself. I
thought it'll be 1 hour, but anyway,
happy to answer your questions. Thank
you so much for the questions and I'm
going to end this live stream here right
now. Tomorrow we have an 8:00 p.m.
episode of the Indian interest in which
we will discuss India US relations and
then we'll do another live stream of
ask. So, thank you so much for watching
and I will see you in the next live
stream. Keep asking questions, keep
raising your standards, and keep
learning. Thank you, and I'll see you
soon. Bye-bye.